Hey all.
Fun to talk to you all from my home office in Helsinki.
The subject of my lecture today is address and tone in government communication.
I have promised to move in the past and show examples of how to do before
before we get back to the present again.
The background to this is -
That I wrote a dissertation that is about addressing in commercials from the 20th century.
Advertising films are something other than government communication
But the collection I work with consists of over 400 films.
Among them are some that were not common commercials
Without rather information films directed from authorities to the public.
The purpose of this dissertation was to illuminate the Dure form -
The most important thing is that commercial players sell
while authorities rather inform.
But on the other hand you can say that informative is also about selling
If not products, at least ideas, attitudes and concepts.
So you want to influence recipients, get the viewer to watch out in traffic, vote in the election
Eat healthy, stop sipping and start exercising.
Both advertising and the information films use classic rhetorical grip -
Like ethos, logos and pathos.
Ethos means that you convince through your person, e.g.
by showing experts.
Logos means that you appeal to reason.
It is perhaps a more common grip for authorities
to get a ration bread or something similar.
But it was also found that the film could be used to teach people in
How to deal with this deficiency.
This article from March 1918 is actually about rational housekeeping and film.
The newest Christian education.
Here we see pictures of how to fry herring without fat.
How to use a very ordinary sleeve case and a hat box for savings.
And how to fry plates of potato flakes, obviously in a tiled stove.
I want to highlight a quote from this article.
(Reading the text)
When I found the quote was the first thing I did to find Fairbanks and Love
Because I wanted something to compare with -
When I then looked at the Food Board's teaching film -
Which is about how to cook and bake bread in the stove.
I would very much like to show it to you, but it is five minutes long
So you have to find it yourself if you are curious.
But what happens in the movie is quite typically
Something that occurs in commercials and housewife films throughout the 20th century.
First we have the Etoskomponent, the male expert who demonstrates for us -
We find it in many war -time newspaper ads where you want to encourage Swedes -
To donate money to Finland or stand up as volunteers in the war.
These ads appeal to the reader with you.
It also makes a road safety campaign.
This movie, which is also a little too long for this context
begins with neutral factual reason arguments -
While we get to see a scene that ends with us seeing a child being hit by a car -
in the lively Stockholm traffic.
At the end, the film turns to a purely pathos-grip-
Where you convince the viewer of the seriousness of this issue with direct you-speech to the viewer.
We see a police officer standing with the lifeless child in their arms
and hear the narrator voice saying:
(Reading the text)
But because of the deeply serious message, it still works.
Dure form is not the only change in the 1960s.
One can see at the same time partially overlapping, but completely revolving changes
which is usually called informalization, democracy, intimisation and conversation.
Dure form is the clearest linguistic cursor, but it happens much more.
This is seen in the films of time that began to use a completely different tone
towards the recipient.
This is an example from the year 1967
When you switched from left -hand traffic to right -hand traffic.
A little info film that reminds the viewer of
That you have to sharpen so that you do not end up on the wrong side when driving in traffic.
I'll play it for you.
Here we can note many new features compared to old films.
That i have colored with green in the text
Are especially clear markers for a new informal and free style.
"Oh you" Here you are used for the viewer, but not as a common address -
but as soon as a discourse marker.
"Mary mode" time -typical youth language, I think.
"So you don't have to do away with it."
Here the movie has the stomach to suggest that the viewer could do away with traffic.
Instead of showing off a grounded end product
If you show something that will represent an insight into the process.
He who is in the middle of the picture is Gottfried Grafström.
He has written a script that is evaluated by actor Birgitta Andersson to the right.
She thinks the script lacks humor and now you should see it.
But there is also a type of government film that is much more straightforward
Teaching and educating.
A splendid example of this was served by the National Board of Health and Welfare in 1975.
This one in itself well - the film today looks so absurd out -
that it has rolled around in social media where it has been commented and discussed.
Often by today's youth who think it is absolutely sick to tell this way
Where today's young people think it is absolutely incredible.
This is exactly what I do not think our authorities are guilty of today.
But that does not mean that we should be completely uncritical to all new opportunities
that opens up for us ... (sound loss)
The social media today, has become a bit like the movie was a hundred years ago.
It is new, you can experiment with new forms of appeal and tone to citizens.
You can fail with it, and then you can easily be perceived as manipulative.
When borrowing languages and other forms from the private sphere
It becomes more difficult for the recipient to identify power.
The link between democratization and informalization is not at all obvious.
But when the new form experiments succeed